Guide to the Marian Parker Whitney Papers, 1842-1945 (bulk 1871-1945)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Marian Parker Whitney Papers
1842-1945
1871-1945
Whitney, Marian P. (Marian Parker), 1861-
6.4 cubic feet (8 boxes and 1 tube)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Materials relating to Whitney's position at Vassar College as well as her involvement with the American Association of University Professors, the International Council of Women, the National Council of Women, Connecticut Association of Working Girls' Clubs, and other women's groups. There are also biographical materials, including correspondence and diaries, containing information about Whitney's family, intellectual pursuits, travels and other personal issues.
Biographical Note
Marian Parker Whitney (1861-1946), was an educator and daughter of the distinguished scholar, William Dwight Whitney. She was born in New Haven, CT, and attended private schools in this country and in Europe. She did graduate work at the Universities of Paris and Zurich and received a Ph.D. from Yale in 1901. After several years of teaching high school in New Haven, Miss Whitney became a professor of German at Vassar in 1905, serving as chairperson of the department for many years. One of her interests was the theater, and she introduced a popular course on contemporary comparative drama. She was author and editor of many French and German grammars and textbooks.
Miss Whitney's interests beyond Vassar were extensive. She was active in professional organizations of language teachers and in the American Association of University Professors. She was deeply concerned with improving women's social and political status. As a leading member of both the National and International Council of Women, Whitney visited Europe in 1919-1920 to study changes in women's education brought about by World War I. A supporter of separate education for women, Miss Whitney served as a trustee of Connecticut College for Women. Her death in 1946 followed a long illness.
Scope and Content Note
Family correspondence includes letters received by her father William Dwight Whitney, 1842-1850; her correspondence with her parents, 1872-1891; and letters received from other family members, 1872-1900. Personal correspondence, 1871-1905, from Jennie and Fannie Bailey, Amanda Brewster, Honor Brooke, Beatrice Chamberlain, Eva Channing, Elizabeth Whitney Putnam, Marie Souvestre, Bessie M. Townsend, and Edith Woolsey concerning intellectual pursuits, travels, Brooke's work with a working girls' club in London (1889), family affairs, and other personal news. Papers from her Vassar position include minutes, reports, materials from her German and drama courses, correspondence with Presidents Taylor and MacCracken, and letters from students. Correspondence, programs, reports, bills, and other items from her work with the American Association of University Professors, the International Council of Women, the National Council of Women, Connecticut Association of Working Girls' Clubs, and other women's groups, 1919-1934. Scrapbooks, class notebooks, and several manuscripts, 1871-1891 and undated; diaries from 1873 to 1945; and correspondence and other materials from trips to Europe, England, and Japan, 1886-1920.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the
regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library
without any additional restrictions.
Subject Headings
Names:
Whitney, William Dwight, 1827-1894; Bailey, Fannie; Bailey, Jennie; Brewster, Amanda; Brooke, Honor; Chamberlain, Beatrice; Channing, Eva; Putnam, Elizabeth Whitney; Souvestre, Marie; Townsend, Bessie M.; Woolsey, Edith; Taylor, James Monroe, 1848-1916; MacCracken, H. N. (Henry Noble), 1880-1970; Whitney family
Organizations:
American Association of University Professors; International Council of Women; National Council of Women of the United States; Connecticut Association of Working Girls' Clubs; Vassar College--Faculty; Vassar College--Students
Subjects:
Family--New York (State)--Poughkeepsie; Women--Societies and clubs; Women--England--London--Societies and clubs; Women--Employment; German language--Study and teaching; Drama--Study and teaching; Women--Diaries; Women college teachers
Places:
Europe--Description and travel; England--Description and travel; Japan--Description and travel
Document Types:
Scrapbooks; Diaries
VCL Categories
Family; Travel; Vassar College; Women's History
Encoding Information
Encoded by Elizabeth Clarke, April 2007.
Acquisition Information
Gift of estate of Emily Whitney.
2 Whitney items were found in Carl Friedrich Gauss's Theoria Mutus Corporum... (Grille 521.3 G237) and added to Multiple Collections at an unknown time. They were transferred from there to the Whitney collection (folder 4.20), March 2007.
Series List
- Series I. Correspondence, (Boxes 1-2)
- Series II. Professional Career, (Boxes 3-4)
- Series III. Women's organizations, (Boxes 5-6)
- Series IV. Miscellaneous, (Box 7, tube)
Container List
- Series I. Correspondence
  - Clippings, pictures, and miscellaneous items relating to family (Folder 1.1)
  - Family letters to William Dwight Whitney, father of M.P. W., 1842-1850 (Folder 1.2)
  - William D. Whitney's letters to M.P. W. and her letters to him, 1872-1891 (Folder 1.3)
  - M.P.W.'s letters to unidentified persons (Folder 1.4)
  - M.P.W.'s letters to her mother's letters to her and other family members (Folders 1.5-1.8)
  - Letters to Emily (sister) from M.P.W. and Emily's letters to her (Folder 1.9-1.10)
  - Emily's letters to her parents and letters from others to her (Folders 1.11-1.12)
  - Letters to Margaret (sister) from M.P.W. and Margaret's letters to her (Folders 1.13-1.14)
  - Letters of Edward B. Whitney (brother), mostly to M.P.W., ca. 1875-1900 (Folders 1.15-1.16)
  - Letters of Josepha (wife of Edward) to M.P.W. and her mother (Folder 1.17)
  - Letters of congratulation to Edward on his appointment as Assistant U.S. Attorney General, 1893 (Folder 1.18)
  - Letters from Emily Baldwin (grandmother), 1872-1873 (Folder 1.19)
  - Letters from Roger Whitney (brother), 1872 (Folder 1.19)
  - Letters of aunts and uncles (Folder 1.20)
  - Letters of "cousins." (Folder 1.21)
  - Letters from "Elizabeth." (Folder 2.1-2.2)
  - Letters from Jennie and Fannie Bailey, 1871-1891 (Folder 2.3)
  - Letters from Amanda Brewster (Folder 2.4)
  - Letters from Honor Brooke, 1880-1898 (Folder 2.5)
  - Letters from Beatrice Chamberlain, 1880-1903 (Folder 2.6-2.7)
  - Letters from Eva Channing, 1879, 1898 (Folder 2.8)
  - Letters from Marie Souvestre, 1880-1896 (Folder 2.9)
  - Marie Souvestre's death, 1905 (Folder 2.9)
  - Letters from Bessie M. Townsend, 1883-1896 (Folder 2.10)
  - Letters from Edith Woolsey (Folder 2.11)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence (Folder 2.12-2.19)
- Series II. Professional Career
  - Honors (Folder 3.1)
  - Ph.D. from Yale (Folder 3.2)
  - Positions and offers of positions prior to Vassar. (Folder 3.3)
  - New Haven High School (Folder 3.4)
  - Appointment Professor of German, Vassar College, 1905 (Folder 3.5)
  - Correspondence with Presidents Taylor and MacCracken. (Folder 3.6)
  - V.C. faculty committees (Folder 3.7)
  - V.C. German Department appointments and leaves. (Folder 3.8)
  - German Department student assistants (Folder 3.9)
  - German Department changes in requirements (Folder 3.10)
  - Letters from students (Folder 3.11)
  - German Department curriculum, 1927 (Folder 3.12)
  - Oral tests in modern languages (Folder 3.13)
  - German Department questions of students (Folder 3.14)
  - Committee on College Lectures (Folder 3.15)
  - Fellowships (Folder 3.16)
  - Visiting lecturers in German Department (Folder 3.17)
  - V.C. comparative drama course (Folder 3.18)
  - Comparative Drama exams (Folder 3.19)
  - Contemporary Drama (Folder 3.20)
  - Contemporary German Drama (Folder 3.21)
  - V.C. German courses (Folder 3.22-3.25)
  - V.C. German graduate courses (Folder 3.26)
  - Modern foreign language study (Folder 3.27)
  - Gustab Falke autobiography (Folder 3.28)
  - V.C. Modern Language Week (Folder 3.29)
  - V.C. German-French Departments (Folder 3.30)
  - Material on German readers by M.P.W (Folder 3.31)
  - Invitations, engagements, and weddings (Folders 4.1-4.2)
  - London, 1886 (Folder 4.3)
  - Canal Boat letters, 1886 (Folder 4.4)
  - Paris, 1895 (Folder 4.5)
  - Europe, 1897-1898 (Folder 4.6-4.7)
  - M.P.W.'s letters from Europe, 1897 (Folder 4.6-4.7)
  - Trip to Japan, 1900 (Folder 4.8)
  - Spain, 1902 (Folder 4.9)
  - England and France, 1904 (Folder 4.10)
  - M.P.W.'s letters from England and Germany, 1908 (Folder 4.11)
  - Passport, 1920 (Folder 4.12)
  - Bills and receipts (Folder 4.13)
  - Carving designs and drawings (Folder 4.14)
  - Saturday Morning club. Programs, correspondences, etc. (Folder 4.15)
  - Organizations (recreational), programs, and hobbies. (Folder 4.16)
  - American Association of University Professors. (Folder 4.17)
  - Connecticut Association of Classical and High School Teachers (Folder 4.18)
  - New England Modern Language Association and MLA (Folder 4.19)
  - Miscellaneous manuscripts and notes (Folder 4.20)
  - Manuscript: "Occupations of Women,", (about 1883?) (Folder 4.21)
  - Manuscript on Josiah Gibbs by Margaret D. Whitney, 1937 (Folder 4.22)
  - German manuscript by unknown author (Folder 4.23)
- Series III. Women's organizations
  - International Council of Women (ICW), General. (Folder 5.1)
  - ICW reports, 1923, 1929-1930 (Folder 5.2)
  - ICW "current business,", 1924 (Folder 5.3)
  - ICW business for Washington Reports, etc., 1925 (Folder 5.4)
  - ICW Washington meeting and conferences, 1925 (Folder 5.5-5.6)
  - ICW correspondence, 1920-1934 (Folder 5.7-5.9)
  - ICW programs, letters, resolutions, etc (Folder 5.10)
  - ICW Bulletins (Folder 5.11)
  - ICW Executive Committee. Meetings at Copenhagen, 1924, and Stockholm, 1933 (Folders 5.12-5.13)
  - ICW Committee on Education. Circular letters, bills, programs, questionnaires, and correspondence (Folders 5.14-5.16)
  - ICW Committee on Education. Reports, and correspondence, 1920-1930 (Folders 5.17-5.18)
  - ICW Committee on Education. Reports, 1925-1930 (Folders 6.1-6.5)
  - ICW Committee on Education. Questionnaires, 1925-1930 (Folder 6.6)
  - ICW Committee on Education, 1931-1934 (Folder 6.7)
  - ICW Committee on Education. Report for Council Meeting, 1934 (Folder 6.8)
  - ICW Film Committee (Folder 6.9)
  - National Council of Women, 1919-1934 (Folders 6.10-6.12)
  - Comite d'Education Feminine (Folder 6.13)
  - Congres International de la Condition et des Droits des Femmes (Folder 6.14)
  - International Federation of University Women. Conference at Edinburgh, 1932 (Folder 6.15)
  - Connecticut Association of Working Girls' Clubs. (Folder 6.16)
- Series IV. Miscellaneous
  - Scrapbook, 1876-1891; (1 volume) (Box 7)
  - Notebooks from George B. Adams' course in medieval institutions, (3 volumes) (Box 7)
  - Class book, 1894; (1 volume) (Box 7)
  - Autograph albums, (2 volumes) (Box 7)
  - Diaries, 1873-1945; (20 volumes) (Box 7)
  - Yale Ph.D. diploma (Tube)